Guide to the Timothy Leary Manuscripts and Ephemera, 1940-1986.
Leary, Timothy Manuscripts and Ephemera
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Timothy Leary Manuscripts and Ephemera, 1940-1986.
8593
McWhinnie, John
.6 cubic feet.
Correspondence, manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The materials by and relating to Leary in this collection were assembled by rare books and contemporary art dealer John McWhinnie.
This collection contains circa 150 items comprised of manuscripts and documents by Leary; letters to and from Leary, including additional correspondence concerning him; documents and manuscripts relating to Leary's colleagues and associates in the psychedelic movement, and the various institutions and organizations they created; and psychedelic-related ephemera.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Timothy Leary (1920-1996) was an American psychologist and writer known for advocating the exploration of the therapeutic potential of psychedelic drugs.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The materials by and relating to Leary in this collection were assembled by rare books and contemporary art dealer John McWhinnie.
This collection contains circa 150 items comprised of manuscripts and documents by Leary; letters to and from Leary, including additional correspondence concerning him; documents and manuscripts relating to Leary's colleagues and associates in the psychedelic movement, and the various institutions and organizations they created; and psychedelic-related ephemera.
SUBJECTS
Names:
McWhinnie, John; Leary, Timothy, 1920-1996.
Subjects:
Drugs.; Psychotropic drugs.; Psychotropic drugs--History.; Psychotropic drugs--Social aspects.; Psychotropic drugs--Therapeutic use.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Leary manuscripts and documents, 1940-1950
  - Typescript photocopy, Declaration of Independence for Dr. Timothy Leary. July 4, 1971 (Draft), 1971-07-04; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Statement defending Leary, with autograph note: "Allen Ginsberg arranged! / [sketch of smiling heart] / "Timothy Leary / 9-19-95." Draft text for pamphlet of the same title.
  - Declaration of Independence for Dr. Timothy Leary. July 4, 1971, 1971-07-04; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Interpersonal Dimension of Personality, 1951-12; Leary, Timothy; Freedman, Mervin (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Reprint from Journal of Personality. Vol. 20, no. 2. December, 1951. Pages 143-161
  - Psychedelic Prayers after the tao te ching, 1966; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 4)
    New Hyde Park, N.Y.: University Books. n.d.
  - Summary of the Dissertation Submitted in Partial Satisfaction of the Requirements for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy, 1950-12; Leary, Timothy Francis (Box 1, Folder 5)
    University of California, Graduate Division, Northern Section.
  - The Neo-American Church Catechism and Handbook: A Review by Timothy Leary, 1967; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A Constructive Proposal to End the LSD Crisis, Undated; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Religious Implications of Consciousness Expanding Substances, 1963-05-1963-06; Leary, Timothy; Clark, Walter Houston (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Reprinted from Religious Education
  - DMT Report, 1962-12-10; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Description of personal DMT experience
  - Session #16 - Zi. Subject #1, Undated; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Untitled mimeographed typescript, 1962-11; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Summary of LSD research at Harvard for a Los Angles audience
  - Starseed Bulletin; Update: July 1974-February 1975, 1975; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 12)
    An addendum describing Leary's recent activities since the publication "of this book" (presumably Starseed).
  - Partly printed check signed, ("Timothy Leary"), 1955-12-01; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Check for five dollars payable to "NAACP," on American Trust Company account, Oakland, CA. Cancellation stamps.
  - School and Society, Volume 64, 1946-07-20; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Contains Leary's essay, "Progress Toward Solving the Problem of Race Relations," (pp. 41-43).
  - Partial Typescript: First LSD Experiment, 1962; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 15)
    A typed description by Leary, heavily annotated, of his first meeting with Huxley, his initial purchase of LSD, and the group they gathered to conduct the first experiment (which included Huxley)
  - Typescript Commodore Leri Story, Undated; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "LSD - Tepoztlan", 1962-06; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Leary's description of taking LSD in Mexico and engaging in a threesome
  - League for Spiritual Discovery, 1966; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Description and purposes of the League for Spiritual Discovery, "a non-profit religious association" which advocated the use of LSD. Leary listed as first member of "Board of Guides" (p.5).
  - United States Corps of Cadets Card, issued to Leary, 1940; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The Religious Experience: Its Production and Interpretation, 1970; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Typescript of "revision of the article on drugs," for Esquire magazine, 1964-03-12; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 21)
    With attached carbon of March 12, 1964 letter (unsigned) from Leary to Harold Hayes, editor of Esquire, resubmitting the manuscript; typewritten corrections throughout
  - Reactions To Psilocybin Administered in a Supportive Environment., 1963-12; Leary, Timothy; Litwin, George H.; Metzner, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Reprint from The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, Vol. 137, No. 6, December 1963
  - Statement by Timothy Leary, 1971; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Leary justifies his plea of not guilty to federal drug charges.
  - Americans and Mushrooms in a Naturalistic Environment: A Preliminary Report, 1962; Leary, Timothy; Litwin, George H.; Metzner, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Annotated Partial Transcript of Interview, 1975; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Three original typescript pages from a longer interview of Leary, which has been heavily edited and emended in autograph, possibly by him.
  - Genetic Roulette Circuit 7, 1972-12; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Original typescript
  - "One night in the winter I crossed the Rockies…", Undated; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Original typescript story featuring Little Richard, Fatty Arbuckle, Floyd Patterson, and talking goats.
  - Draft annotated typescript, "HIP — new lead.", Undated; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Original typescript of article describing a San Francisco peace rally.
  - A New Behavior Change Program Using Psilocybin, 1965; Leary, Timothy; Metzner, Ralph; Weil, Gunther; Schwitzgebel, Ralph; Kinne, Sara (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Typescript essay, untitled. ("A journalist in the Haight-Ashbury is hung on a strange dilemma."), Undated; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Annotated in Leary's hand
  - Letter from James Goddard, 1966-04-05; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Autograph notes in pencil and ink, on verso of circular letter, unsigned, from James Goddard, Commissioner of Food and Drugs
  - A group of photocopied legal contracts between Leary and Michel- Gustave Hauchard relating to the publishing and film rights of various Leary works, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Many with original ink annotations in Leary's hand
- Series II: Letters to and from Leary (and among his circle), 1961-1988
  - Typed letter signed, "G" to "Timothy &.", 1966-04-04; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Photocopies of Correspondence with Allen Ginsburg, 1962-1963; Ginsburg, Allen (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Photocopies of Correspondence with Aldous Huxley, 1962-1963; Huxley, Aldous (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Autograph Letter Signed to Michael Hollengshead, 1968-12-09; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Report on his happiness and optimism about his legal situation: "We too are enjoying Heaven…"
  - Typed letter signed, "Tim" to "Attorney.", 1970; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 36)
    With: Photocopy of "United States of America vs. Timothy Leary: Change of Counsel."
  - Autograph Letter Signed "T' to Dr. Gene Schoenfeld, 1973-03-01; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Autograph letter signed, "T" to "Michael", 1973-03-01; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Leary thanks him for sending various publications and speculates about possible titles for his forthcoming book.
  - Autograph letter signed, "James Peter Cavagnaro" to "Jan.", Undated; Cavagnaro, James Peter (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Writing from prison, he praises Leary's and Hesse's ideas on liberation and spiritual energy.
  - Typed letter signed, "Walter" to "Betsy.", 1973-04-06; Clark, Walter Houston (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Together with: Appeal Against Further Trial & Persecution of Dr. Timothy Leary
  - Typed letter signed, "Arthur Kleps" to "Mr. Volkening.", 1964-06-08; Kleps, Arthur. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Typed letter signed, "Paul" to "Tim or whoever.", 1964-11-20; Krassner, Paul (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Krassner inquiring if Leary will be conducting a seminar at Millbrook in late November
  - Typed letter signed, "Paul" to "Tim, Dick, and Ralph.", 1964-09-27; Krassner, Paul (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Krassner informing Leary that his new article was to be entitled "Dr. Leary – or How I Learned to Transcend Ego and Expand My Consciousness (Notes from a Found Weekend)."
  - Typed note signed, "A.C. Spectorsky" to "Dr. Leary.", 1966; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Stapled to: Typed letter signed, from "Tim Leary" to "Mr.Spectorsky." With: Playboy Interview: Timothy Leary. Also with: Leary, Timothy. Typescript on Ira Cohen, LSD, and Cannabis
  - Autograph letter signed, "Alan" to "Tim.", 1963-05-29; Watts, Alan (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Watts states that the both the FDA and Myron Stolaroff of the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) suspected the current liquid LSD in circulation had very serious impurities
  - Typed letter signed in type, "Your Flower Peter" to "Dr. Timothy Leary.", 1961-01-05; Orlovsky, Peter (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Orlovsky — Ginsberg's lover — writing Leary about his experiences with LSD.
  - Autograph letter signed, "Ron" to "Tim", Undated; Thelin, Ron (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Typed letters signed, "Art Kleps" to "Dr. Kissinger" and "Editor, Time Magazine.", 1973-06-06-1973-04-25; Kleps, Arthur (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Kleps writes Kissinger in the midst of the Watergate crisis, and states the good that might come if the conspirators ended up in the same prison as Leary
  - Typed letter signed, "T" to "Beloved Joanna", Undated; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 49)
    A draft of Leary's "Signal From Galactic Transmission Center to Planet Earth," which presents as "call home" from extraterrestrial species to the human race.
  - Typed letter signed, from "Richard Alpert" to "Dr. Hofmann", 1963-02-01; Alpert, Richard (Box 1, Folder 50)
    A letter written by Alpert on behalf of Leary, who was in Mexico at the time.
  - Typed letter signed, to Dr. Humphry Osmond, with partial draft, Metzner, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Metzner disputes Osmond's critical positionson both the Psychedelic Review and Leary.
  - Autograph note signed, "Arthur" to unknown, Undated; Kleps, Arthur (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Describing his travel plans
  - Typed letter signed, from "Ralph" to "Joel.", 1964; Metzner, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Metzger encloses (not present) several brochures about upcoming psychedelic seminars and workshops.
  - Typed letter signed, from "Frances" to "Timothy.", Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Autograph letter signed, "Dr. Rene Bouvier.", Undated; Bouvier, Rene (Box 1, Folder 55)
    On verso: Family Dog Presents Poster.
  - Large brown mailing envelope, annotated and signed by Timothy Leary, 1988-08; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Series III: Leary's circle, 1963-1971
  - Typescript Speech, 1963; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 81)
    A typewr
  - Psychedelic Religious Celebrations, 1966; League for Spiritual Discovery (Box 1, Folder 82)
    Announcement of League for Spiritual Discovery meetings.
  - The LSD Spiritual Revolution and Technological Change, 1971; League for Spiritual Discovery (Box 1, Folder 83)
    Sent as mailer; verso of second leaf franked and addressed in autograph from "B Ehrlich" in Van Nuys, CA
  - Come and Share in the Magic of Millbrook Weekend Live-Ins, Undated; League for Spiritual Discovery (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - The Illumination of the Buddha, Undated; League for Spiritual Discovery (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - How to Use Your Head, 1964; Psychedelic Review (Box 1, Folder 86)
    Bibliography: Recent Publications About Theories and Research on Psychedelic Experiences.
  - How to Play Trans-Personative Games, Undated; IFIF (Box 1, Folder 87)
    With Photocopy of drawing of word sections; "Me" in the center
  - Application for Membership to International Federation for Internal Freedom (IFIF), 1963-03-12; Kesey, Ken (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Program for the Re-Affirmation of the Eternal Union of Carol Mann and Bob Ross, Undated (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Millbrook
    With: Printed card, naming Leary as "presiding p
  - Psychedelic Festival Theatre Invitations, 1966; Leary Defense Fund (Box 1, Folder 90)
    Invitation to a benefit for the Timothy Leary Defense Fund
  - Neo-American Church Catechism and Handbook Brochure, Undated; Kleps, Arthur (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Emended Castalia Foundation Brochure, 1964; Castalia (Box 1, Folder 92)
    Together with: Card insert: "How to Use Your Head." Mass mailer for presentation by Leary and Alpert on Sunday, November 29, 1964, at Town Hall in New York. Leary has amended the brochure to eliminate both the Castalia Foundation and Richard Alpert's names throughout, and change the title to "Psychedelic Workshops Conducted by Timothy Leary, Ph.D. and Ralph Metzner, Ph.D."
  - Psychedelic Sweatshirts Ordering Form Mailer, 1965; Millbrook (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - The Stoned and...The Unstoned, Undated; Kleps, Arthur (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Membership Application to "The Neo-American Church.", Undated; Kleps, Arthur (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Neo-American Church Bulletins, 1965-12-1966-09; Kleps, Arthur (Box 1, Folder 96)
    Invitation to a public baseball tournament, as well as other psychedelic news.
  - Selected Bibliography on the Safety of LSD-25, Undated; Metzner, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 97)
    A small selection of books and articles supporting the safety of LSD, some with additional quotes and reviews.
  - Castalia Foundation Lecture Announcement Postcard, 1965; Castalia (Box 1, Folder 98)
    An announcement for a lecture by Leary and Richard Alpert.
  - Program Flyer for Psychedelic Explorations, 1965; Castalia (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Psychedelic Religious Celebration #1 and #2, Undated; League for Spiritual Discovery (Box 1, Folder 100)
    Program for a League event, with Leary acting as "Guide," Ralph Metzner as "Harry, the Imprisoned Intellectual," and others in other roles.
  - Psychedelic Review Subscription Materials, 1963; Psychedelic Review (Box 1, Folder 101)
    The Psychedelic Review with TLS, from Felix Morrow and Ralph Metzger as well as a Psychedelic Review Subscription Direct Mail Package.
  - International Federation for Internal Freedom Membership Package, 1963; IFIF (Box 1, Folder 102)
    Including; Statement on LSD and Psilocybin; Application for Membership; I.F.I.F. Newsletters; Marketing Letter, Typed, to "Dear Friend" from Leary; Present Program: IFIF – Cambridge; New Statement of Purposes; Sample Letter Draft; Paradise Lost by Mexico LSD Colony; Page 3 of Mimeograph Letter; Note.
  - Psychedelic Sessions, 1965-1966 Fall/Winter; Psychedelic Review (Box 1, Folder 103)
    A marketing brochure for a series of workshops led by Leary and Metzger
  - Castalia Foundation Experiential Workshops, 1965; Castalia (Box 1, Folder 104)
    A marketing brochure for a series of weekend workshops led by Leary, Metzner, and Alpert at the Castalia Foundation in Millbrook.
  - On "Alternative Realities," "Biverses," "Multiverses" and Occultism in General, Undated; Kleps, Arthur (Box 1, Folder 105)
    An excerpt from Kleps's longer text, Millbrook.
  - An Introduction to the Field of Consciousness Expansion, 1965-12; O'Brien, Desmond (Box 1, Folder 106)
    With an Outline of the Effects and Usage of the Psychedelic Drugs
  - Chromosomal Abnormalities in Leukocytes From LSD-25 Users, Undated; Irwin, Samuel; Egozcue, Jose (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - The Avatar of You is You, Undated; Kleps, Arthur (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Notes On Current Research, 1968; Metzner, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Castalia Foundation Millbrook Summer School Psychedelic Training Courses Brochure, 1966; Castalia (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Proposal for research on consciousness-altering drugs, 1962; Metzner, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 111)
    A request for an $11,000 grant to study the effects of psilocybin and mescaline at Harvard, with Leary and Alpert among the "consultants."
  - The Three Who Made a Revolution, Undated; Graboi, Nina (Box 1, Folder 112)
    A study of the work of Leary, Alpert and Metzner
  - Points of Distinction Between Sedative and Hallucinogenic Drugs, Undated; Burroughs, William (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Bay Area Writers Appeal to Swiss Government for Leary Political Asylum, 1971; Leary Defense (Box 1, Folder 114)
    Statement Signed by Kesey, Ferlinghetti and Others, Calls Leary Fellow Author Without Country
  - Mimeograph Typescript "#10", Undated; Alpert, Richard (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Opening line: "The plan of this session was to have a solo experience."
  - LSD, Chromosomes and Sensationalism, 1968; Fort, Joel; Metzner, Ralph (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Psychedelic Review #10.
  - An American Sense, Undated; Creeley, Robert (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript Poem, Undated; Castalia (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript Poem, untitled, Undated; Millbrook (Box 2, Folder 5)
    On Millbrook and LSD
  - Autograph Poem, Undated; Unknown (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Begins: "Art if not life, what? Life if not art, why?..."
  - Draft of The LSD Issue: A New Look at the World, Undated; Block, Joel N. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript Notes for The LSD Issue: A New Look at the World, Undated; Block, Joel N. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The LSD Issue: A New Look at the World, Undated; Block, Joel N. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    A typescript teleplay for video featuring Dana Farnsworth, Dr. Theodore Rothman, Dr. Roy Grinker, and various experimental subjects, among others. No record of it having been produced has been found. Hitchcock-Balding Productions, to which the teleplay is addressed, also produced several of Leary's live speaking events, and had been engaged by the League of Spiritual Discovery to handle their public business.
  - Timothy Leary Defense Fund Declaration of Principle, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Leary Defense Fund
  - Committee for the Reform of Marihuana Laws Statement of Purpose, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Psychedelic ephemera, 1962-1986
  - Acid Beat presents the Psychedelic Glossary, 1986; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Psychedelic Peace Fellowship Affirmation of Purpose and Membership Application, 1966-09-16-1966-10-17; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Perception '67 Schedule of Events, 1967; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Listing a lecture by Leary on "Psychedelics and Religion."
  - A Gathering of the Tribes for a Human Be-In Poster, 1967-01-14; Leary, Timothy (Box 1, Folder 60)
    List of performers includes Ginsberg and Leary.
  - Printed program for The LSD Conference, 1966-06-13-1966-06-18; LSD Conference (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Dwight H. Buckley Bifoliates, 1966; Buckley, Dwight H. (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Greater Freedom for the Socio-Economic Bind Through Fasting; Psycles Research; A Safe and Successful Program For the Solving of Human Problems and the transformation of Lives
  - Freedom Center, Inc. Newsletter, 1962-11-30; Freedom Center, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Declaration on the LSD Crisis, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - First Meeting (organizational) of the tentative Society for Psychedelic Research, 1964-01-23; Society for Psychedelic Research (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Probe 1, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Free University of Berkeley Spring 1969 Catalogue, 1969; Free University of Berkeley (Box 1, Folder 67)
    First course listed, on cover, is "Psychedelic Psychology," taught by Leary.
  - HAIL: Haight-Ashbury-Ink-Link Newsletter, 1967-04; Haight-Ashbury Neighborhood Council (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - LSD and the Psychedelic Movement. Printed lecture program, 1967; Oregon State System of Higher Education (Box 1, Folder 69)
    Listing a schedule of lectures in Portland, Oregon
  - MARIJUANA. Broadside, Undated; LEMAR (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Issued by the Detroit, Michigan group, LEMAR, calling for the legalization of marijuana.
  - Darwin Missed La Mark, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Free University of Berkeley Pamphlet, 1968; Free University of Berkeley (Box 1, Folder 72)
    Pamphlet for "psychedelic" classes in fall 1968.
  - Can Drugs Lead You to God?, Undated; Aiken, John W. (Box 1, Folder 73)
    Originally published in Fate Magazine in May, 1963.
  - Physics as a Mandala for Human Consciousness, 1967; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 74)
    Two Drafts
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - D.A.R.E. (Drug Abuse Research and Education)
  - Notes on the Effect of the "Magic Mushroom" on my own Person, 1962-05-01; Olson, C.T. (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Newsletter #2, 1967-07; Psychedelic Information Center (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Informational sheet about the "LSD Line.", Undated; Peters, George (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Physics/Consciousness Research Group, Undated; Sarfatti, Jack (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Psilocybin Project, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 80)
    Details observations from experiment on a 25-year-old poet on psilocybin.